Chapter 27. Knights and squires.
Stub was the second mate. He was a native of Cape Cod, and hence, according
to local usage, he was called a Cape Codman, a happygolucky, neither craven
nor valiant, taking perils as they came with an indifferent heir, and while
engaged in the most imminent crisis of the chase, toiling away calm and
collected as a journeyman joiner, engaged for the year. Good humored,
easy, and careless, he presided over his whaleboat, as if the most deadly
encounter were but a dinner, and his crew all invited guests. He was as
particular about the comfortable arrangement of his part of the boat, as
an old stage driver is about the snugness of his box. When close to the
whale in the very death lock of the fight, he handled his unpitting lance
coolly and off-handedly, as a whistling tinker his hammer. He would hum over his
old rig tunes while flank and flank with the most exasperated monster. Long usage
had for this stub converted the jaws of death into an easy chair. What he
thought of death itself there was no telling. Whether he ever thought of it
at all might be a question, but if he ever did chance to cast his mind that
way after a comfortable dinner, no doubt, like a good sailor, he took it to
be a sort of a call to the watch to tumble aloft and be themselves there
about something which he would find out when he obeyed the order, and not sooner.
What perhaps with other things made Stubs such an easygoing, unfearing man,
so cheerfully trudging off with the burden of life in a world full of grave
peddlers, all bowed to the ground with their packs. What helped to bring about
that almost impious good humor of his?
That thing must have been his pipe, for like his nose, his short black little
pipe was one of the regular features of his face. You would almost as soon have
expected him to turn out of his bunk without his nose as without his pipe. He
kept a whole row of pipes there, ready loaded, stuck in a rack, within easy
reach of his hand. And whenever he turned in, he smoked them all out in
succession, lighting one from another to the end of the chapter, then loading
them again to be in readiness a new. For when Stub dressed, instead of first
putting his legs into his trousers, he put his pipe into his mouth. I say this
continual smoking must have been one cause at least of his peculiar
disposition, for everyone knows that this earthly air, whether ashore or
afloat, is terribly infected with the nameless miseries of the numberless
mortals who have died exhaling it. And as in a time of chalera some people go
about with camperated handkerchiefs to their mouths. So likewise against all
mortal tribulations, Stubs tobacco smoke might have operated as a sort of disinfecting agent.
The third mate was Flask, a native of Tisbury and Martha's Vineyard, a short,
stout, ruddy young fellow, very pugnacious concerning Wales, who somehow
seemed to think that the great Leviathans had personally and hereditarily affronted him, and
therefore it was a sort of point of honor with him to destroy them whenever
encountered. So utterly lost was he to all sense of reverence for the many
marvels of their majestic bulk and mystic ways, and so dead to anything
like an apprehension of any possible danger from encountering them, that in
his poor opinion the wondrous whale was but a species of magnified mouse, or at
least water rat, requiring only a little circumvention and some small application
of time and trouble in order to kill and boil. This ignorant, unconscious
fearlessness of his made him a little waggish in the matter of whales. He
followed these fish for the fun of it, and a three years voyage round Cape Horn
was only a jolly joke that lasted that length of time. As a carpenter's nails
are divided into rot nails and cut nails, so mankind may be similarly
divided. Little flask was one of the rot ones, made to clinch tight and last
long. They called him kingpost on board the Peekquad because in form he could be
well likened to the short square timber known by that name in Arctic whalers and
which by the means of many radiating side timbers inserted into it serves to
brace the ship against the icy concussions of those battering seas.
Now these three mates Starbucks, Stub, and Flask were momentous men. They it
was who by universal prescription commanded three of the Peekquad's boats
as headmen in that grand order of battle in which Captain Ahab would probably
marshall his forces to descend on the whales. These three headsmen were as
captains of companies or being armed with their long keen whailing spears,
they were as a picked trio of lancers, even as the harpooners were flingers of
javelins. And since in this famous fishery each mate or headsman like a
Gothic knight of old is always accompanied by his boat skewer or
harpooner who in certain conjunctures provides him with a fresh lance when the
former one has been badly twisted or elbowed in the assault. And moreover, as
there generally subsists between the two, a close intimacy and friendliness,
it is therefore but meat that in this place we set down who the Peekquad's
harpooners were, and to what headsmen each of them belonged. First of all was
Quiquig, whom Starbucks, the chief mate, had selected for his squire, but
Quiquake is already known.
Next was Tash Tego, an unmixed Indian from Gayhead, the most westerly
promontory of Martha's Vineyard, where there still exists the last remnant of a
village of Red Men, which has long supplied the neighboring island of
Nantucket with many of her most daring harpooners. In the fishery, they usually
go by the generic name of Gay Headers.
Tashego's long, lean, sable hair, his high cheekbones and black rounding eyes,
for an Indian oriental in their largeness, but Antarctic in their
glittering expression, all this sufficiently proclaimed him an inheritor
of the unviated blood of those proud warrior hunters, who, in quest of the
great New England moose, had scoured bow in hand the Aboriginal forests of the
Maine. But no longer snuffing in the trail of the wild beasts of the
woodland, Tashego now hunted in the wake of the great whales of the sea, the
unairring harpoon of the sun, fitly replacing the infallible arrow of the
sires. To look at the tawny brawn of his li snaky limbs, you would almost have
credited the superstitions of some of the earlier Puritans, and half believe
this wild Indian to be a son of the prince of the powers of the air. Tashego
was Stub the second mate squire.
Third among the harpooners was Dagu, a gigantic coal black negro savage with a
lion-like tread and aashvro to behold.
Suspended from his ears were two golden hoops so large that the sailors called
them ring bolts and would talk of securing the top sail howiards to them.
In his youth, Dagu had voluntarily shipped on board a whaler, lying in a
lonely bay on his native coast, and never having been anywhere in the world
but in Africa, Nantucket, and the pagan harbors most frequented by whalemen, and
having now led for many years the bold life of the fishery in the ships of
owners uncommonly heedful of what manner of men they shipped, Dagu retained all
his barbaric virtues, and erect as a giraffe, moved about the decks, in all
the pomp of 6'5 in his socks. There was a corporeal humility in looking up at
him, and a white man standing before him seemed a white flag come to beg truce of
a fortress. Curious to tell, this imperial negro, a hash dagu, was the
squire of little flask, who looked like a chessman beside him. As for the
residue of the Peekquad's company, be it said that at the present day, not more
than one in two of the many thousand men before the mast employed in the American
whale fishery are Americans born, though pretty nearly all the officers are.
Herein it is the same with the American whale fishery as it is with the American
army and military and merchant navies and the engineering forces employed in
the construction of the American canals and railroads. The same, I say, because
in all these cases the Native American liberally provides the brains, the rest
of the world is generously supplying the muscles. No small number of these
whailing seammen belong to the Azors, where the outwardbound Nantucket whalers
frequently touch to augment their crews from the hardy peasants of those rocky
shores. In like manner, the Greenland whalers, sailing out of Hull or London,
put in at the Shetland Islands to receive the full compliment of their
crew. Upon the passage homeward, they dropped them there again. How it is,
there is no telling, but islanders seem to make the best whalemen. They were
nearly all islanders in the Peekquad.
Isolates too, I call such, not acknowledging the common continent of
men, but each isolato living on a separate continent of his own. Yet now,
federated along one keel, what a set these isolates were. An anacarus clut's
deputation from all the isisles of the sea and all the ends of the earth
accompanying old Ahab in the Peekquad to lay the world's grievances before that
bar from which not very many of them ever come back. Black little Pip, he
never did. Oh no, he went before. Poor Alabama boy on the grim peekquad's
folks. who shall he long see him beating his tambourine prolusive of the eternal
time when sent for to the great quarter deck on high he was bid strike in with
angels and beat his tambourine in glory called a coward here hailed a hero there